hi welcome to the eev blog an
Electronics engineering video blog of
interest to anyone involved in
electronics design I'm your host Dave
[Music]
Jones yep okay I'm back on uh as you can
see I'm obviously not in the lab because
it went horrifically wrong I promised a
good show and sure enough
I ruined the KN wife's notebook
woohoo she's pissed um she can hear me
too she's um I thought she wasn't uh she
was going to be at work today but she's
um taking a roster she gets roster she
get actually gets days off and she's
here and uh I can hear her in the
kitchen and she's pretty pissed so um
yeah it looks like the water got in the
notebook and it shut down it just shut
down un un believable um I'm trying to
get it going again but um it's
really um I
it's oh here we go it's now booting it's
now oh well it's now actually switching
on so um hang on let me switch it back
off I'm actually getting blue lights now
it wasn't even um acknowledging the soft
power switch before so now it's actually
um acknowledging the switch anyway um
yeah I won't mck around trying to fix a
notebook cuz this ain't some geek it uh
show so there you
go yeah I fixed it I think the uh
there's the hard drive out of it and uh
uh there's the hard drive bracket and um
it's all going back together couple of
screws lying around so there'll probably
be a screw left over when I put it back
together but um hopefully it'll work
because um oh she wasn't cared about the
notebook all she cared about was a
couple of files on there which she's
been working days on so if I don't get
those files back I'm in deep [__] really
so there you
go all right um so obviously we're not
in the lab anymore how's the frame rate
by the way the frame rate looks really
good on my screen here so um I'm not
sure if that's translating through on
the stream it's good better much better
15 plus frames per second wow okay well
um I should probably um try this is my
old crappy webcam like 5-year-old webcam
that I filmed my very first blog on um
and yeah I just um forgot I had it and
uh I probably should have tried that as
a plugin to The Notebook um because I
don't have um I can't move my other
computer out there I've got to use the
Wireless Notebook to actually get the
connection so there you go um so I'll
give that a go once I get the notebook
fixed it's one of those little isus um
ee PCS it's a 1,000 he or something like
that the one with a 10hour battery life
which is pretty cool um so and it's her
little baby I gave it to her as a
present and now I've screwed it oh God
anyway all she cares about us the
files so it it should come good I mean
unless water actually physically got in
the hard drive water was actually on top
of the hard drive it had actually got in
very quick so there you go
um anyway let's get on with the show
shall we how many viewers I've still got
I still got 67 viewers thanks for
hanging in brilliant I promised a good
show and uh
well you got to see me screw up live how
awesome is that
excellent all right now let's um start
with questions what's the time um 8:38
I'll probably call it quits at um just
after 9: or something like that cuz I do
actually have a pain job I've got to get
to so um I I sort of make my own hours
so it's all right but um yeah so let's
um let's take some questions shall we
I'm going to I'm looking at the chat
window here and
uh uh let's have a
look
um like spark F raising my hand
someone's dude monkey dude monkey raised
his hand so what's your question dude
monkey there's a question on Alum p pcbs
or do some
pract mount mosfets on an aluminum plate
thick cofy tracers do you have some
practice on this and what is the
cheapest way to get a couple of samples
um the tooling is very expensive um
Mount SMD Moss sets on um no you got got
to well there's ways to do it but you
can mount um but you can aluminium pcbs
aren't that expensive if you go to one
of the cheap Chinese manufacturers um
they shouldn't be but you know when
you're doing stuff like that you just
got to pay the money really
um uh this show is awesome already
thanks Master
burner buy yourself a tough book you
insist on drowning laptops well see the
thing is I was um normally I only drink
it I have a drink container with a screw
top lid it's a stainless steel um water
container I was going to take that out
there just for those last incidents but
because I was running late and I thought
oh water water quick and the wife gave
me some in uh a actual glass in two
glasses and so I had two glasses sitting
there and that was that was a big
mistake so
oops make a t-shirt out of a laptop
issue um someone keeps asking what are
College e classes like um they suck
basically um yeah what more can I say um
boring his
batshit what you do sit there doing
Maxwell's equations all the time give me
a break anyway
um how uncomfortable is that couch is
sleeping on tonight yeah I'm in deep
trouble DM Landrum almost 34 years old
going back to college and wondering you
think there's still room for an analog
specialist since this seems to be my
area of Interest yes um analog um
Specialists are few and far between um
my mate Doug Ford who You' seen who saw
in a recent video he's an analog
specialist um he really doesn't do
anything else he does analog um you know
power supplies he doesn't know anything
about micros and he does big Power
Electronics and stuff like that and he's
got a very good business um out of that
highly sought after so um yeah there's
you know and I've heard the same thing
in the US as well there's plenty of call
for analog um Specialists especially in
the chip design area but that's a whole
different uh thing
so yep um yes Chris is raising his hand
um sorry I didn't get back to that other
dude um I have a noob question do I have
to incur another n charge if I change my
design only slightly um I assume you're
referring to pcbs Yes um you do have to
pay another NRE if you change um any of
the layers typically if you change any
of the Gerber layers or even the silk
screen overlay if they've already gone
and printed um if they've already done
the mask for that then yes you'll have
to be up for the NRE cost again so
that's an unfortunate cost many times
I've sent my file off to the PCB
manufacturer and then a couple of hours
later I've realized I've made a mistake
and I've got to a quickly email them
stop stop work you know and I'll send
you some new files sorry we've already
um we we we've already started the job
and we've already made the mask and
you'll have to pay a new
n anyway happens all the time um what
program do I use to design pcbs um
Altium designer but let's not go there
um Altium protel I've been using for 20
plus years so um yeah alium and
protel
um tell us about the license plate um
yeah license plate out in the lab I
won't go get it but the license plate is
a replica from my favorite movie Back to
the Future and if you've been watching
the blog for uh quite some time you'll
know that I'm always throwing well if
you're aware of it I'm always throwing
in little back to the future references
hence my t-shirt my uh flux capacitor
t-shirt which you can buy on the uh
merchandise
um uh page and um that's my own
handdrawn flux capacitor from the movie
which they took down there's a whole
blog on that if you haven't seen it
um and um yes the out of time number
plate I'm just a huge fan of Back to the
Future and I thought it would be a cool
thing it's a replica number plates got
exactly the same stickers on it and
everything so it's very cool very I love
my number plate so I thought I'd just
stick it in the background there and the
OU of time symbol I I think it's just
great you know the out of time thing
it's just I'm always out of time to do
the blog so I think it's quite out next
question
um now I do need a drink but I'm not
going to get a glass of water this time
I'm going to Soldier
on Dave how did you start your formal
electronic study at 15 um well I left
school and I went straight to um well
what we call uh College here is
different to college in the US which is
University I went to college here when I
was 15 and started studying Electronics
because I couldn't uh I couldn't hang
around for another uh two years of high
school I thought that was [__] so um
learning nothing so I went straight off
to um uh College here Technical College
and started studying Electronics when I
was 15 um I finished that course when I
was 17 um oh and continued on after that
but um then I got my first job at 17 in
the industry so there you go next
question
um how about a tutorial on PCB design
techniques or a book suggestion on the
subject um books I don't books are hard
to get on Just generic PCB layout you
can get books on high-speed digital
design and aspects like that um you know
H I won't rattle name off the top of my
head I can't um I'm hopeless at that but
um yeah there are books but not on just
generic uh PCB layout so I'll probably
do some blogs on that cuz I did a trial
with the screen capture thing um last
week with that uh with my latest blog
capturing the digi key screens and all
that and that seemed to work quite well
so I might do a uh a Blog on pcv design
sometime but there's so many aspects to
it I'd have to break it down into
individual topics and do like a 10-part
blog or something like that um
okay yeah everyone Buy the T-shirt so I
get the profits to pay for my off in my
wife's notebook
um is it possible to get 20 kilow out of
a battery that's mounted to a bike
um yeah of course if you got a big
enough battery and it's already
pre-charged you can um I don't know the
energy off the top of my head but you'd
have to get um you could probably get it
out pre-charged but riding a bike you're
only going to get about I think it's
about 500 odd Watts if you're going the
average person riding a bike going flat
out I think can generate you know 500
watts or something like that of actual
energy and then you got conversion
efficiency so if you're charging a
battery or developing power in real time
from a bike you're only going to get you
know a couple hundred Watts out of it or
something like that going at Full Steam
so um don't quote me on that there just
figures off the top of my head um would
I ever consider doing a Blog on the
parallx propeller chip um I haven't used
it it's it's novel you know it's with
its parallel um architecture it's
multiple calls you can run different
threads at the same time and and things
like that and it's got VGA output I
believe and it's it's a nice little chip
no one's ever going to use it in
industry it's just one of those hobbiest
um things it seems to be gaining a bit
of popularity I don't know maybe one day
if I get a dev kit for it or something
like that and I play around maybe but I
don't really think so um not for the
time
being Dave you're etching your own
prototype pcbs um I used to etch my own
type pcbs I've got a light box which I
made with the UV lamps and I've got a
glass thing with clamps and um I just
laser print the um trans laser print the
overhead transparencies that's how I
used to do it but I don't do it anymore
it's just not worth the hassle uh really
making my own board so um I just send
them off to PCB cart or somebody else
and just get them made um it costs a bit
more but it's just no hassle and you get
professional silk screen solder mask
plated through and you know making my
own bards I'm well past that
um uh maybe you could revise the PCB
design tutorial yes I wrote the PCB
design tutorial in like um a weekend or
a day or something over a weekend
because um the reason that came about is
I've always wanted to do a PCB design
tutorial I thought but it always seems
so hard and then I talked to Leo Simpson
the editor silicon chip magazine and and
I said hey I think I could probably do a
PCB design tutorial and he said um oh
great you know F we've been thinking
about doing the same thing but we don't
know how to go about it and I went well
I'll have something for you on Monday so
um yeah I wrote it over the weekend and
it's huge massive amount of downloads
now I've made it available as a PDF and
I get um lots of money from the Google
ads from that website too that's a big
um earner for me actually just that PCB
design to tutorial page so um yeah I'm
keeping that up there but yeah I've
always promised to expand it and stuff
and it's just time really so
yep um do I only Tinker with modern
stuff or play around for tubes and
analog stuff um well analog's still
modern there's
nothing um ancient about analog really
um tubes no I've never been into tubes
and you know all that sort of stuff
Nixie tube displays that doesn't
you know they're kind of cool but I've
never really been fascinated by that I'm
more of a I grew up in the solid state
era so you know um yeah no I don't like
that old stuff it doesn't really
interest me
um what else have we got here um this
looks pretty [__] so I'm not looking at
the camera I'm just looking at the chat
window here and
um oh fpga not to start a holy war but
zyink or
ala jeez you know how long's a piece of
string really um zyink is prob zyink
well is almost certainly the most
popular I think um altia are pretty darn
good and the other vendors out there you
know um actel and stuff like that they
got some cool devices
so pick a dev kit toss a coin pick a dev
kit and go for it really
um yeah it it really makes no difference
in the end they all got Zink and ARA um
both have similar competing technology
what you can do with one you can do with
the other they've got similar chips so
really it doesn't matter
um um as a student pursuing an interest
in embedded design applications what
degree track would you recommend uh well
oh degrees are all different all around
the world so it's hard to kind of say
Australia is going to be different to
the US and all sorts of things but um
really it's all about the software these
days it really is if you're into um
embedded embedded design okay well that
includes Hardware but embedded Hardware
design is not not that hard so um if you
do just a regular e degree you're going
to learn about embedded stuff but um
really a lot of embedded programmers
just are computer science um guys who
are very um computer science degrees who
just are very fluent in C++ and all that
you know really hardcore and the web
enabled stuff these days cuz all these
uh embedded applications are all web
enabled you know you've got to talk
ethernet you've got to talk um IP stacks
and TCP IP and all that sort of stuff so
you really have to be a software Guru to
do the whole embedded application show I
suck it um those real you know those big
interface protocols for embedded um
stuff my software skills just aren't
that um Advanced for you know right my
my own TCP IP stack or troubleshooting
in a TCP IP stack or something like that
so yeah really um anything with a higher
software um bent on it really
um what else have we got
um you won't really learn much from uni
yeah definitely
um yes the best electronics guys do
stuff outside of uni don't rely on uni
or any other study to teach you what you
want to know because it's just not
really um you know very few people come
out and uni being really really good
they just you know they just don't the
ones who are passionate and do it
outside of uni are the ones who are
going to win for sure
um things are being censored on the chat
there's it's obviously killing some uh
killing some Choice terms there on the
chat
um pick a union with a good student
union
geez what percentage of your time at
work do you actually spend doing
Electronics design as opposed to testing
Etc well not a huge amount of
electronics design these days um it's
there's lots of um FP PGA stuff and
[__] around and just testing things
and setting up production test Jigs and
stuff like that um so yeah it varies it
comes and goes I might be solid for a
month um doing Electronics design and
layout and then the next couple of
months I might spend you know doing none
at all and um just you know setting up
some production test software or
something like that um so yeah it varies
all the time but that's my current job
anyway um
who did I look up to um can you be more
specific um Mr
bbbb school sucks yeah
um oh come come on any more questions I
can't really see any huge questions
there so come on throw me a
couple someone's calling somebody a
douche oh was is a douche the was ah
yeah he's a bit of a he's a bit lame but
he's the was so you know got to give him
uh credit for
that um do I have any experience with
zigby uh not a huge amount um no I've
you know played around with it but uh
not a huge amount especially down in the
protocol stack area once again that
software stack kind of thing um not
really
uh recommended language for writing a
quick and easy PC interface um I still
use Visual Basic um I think visual
basic's pretty cool um so I use an old
version of Visual Basic I don't know
what the current one is or anything like
that so um
how can a software developer manage to
design Electronics um do I recommend do
they just read the art of electronics
well um that's where the hobby thing
comes in you can be a software uh person
and just um and have an aid interest in
Hardware outside and that's going to be
enough for you to get byy in a job and
um do the hardware and the software I
think so um yeah it's just a matter of
what your experience is it doesn't
matter where you got that experience
whether you have a formal degree in it
or or what it doesn't doesn't make any
difference at all um so you can
certainly learn Hardware on the on the
side um the same with software as well
so you can be a you know a hardware
qualified Hardware guy and and learn
software and be good at software
so
um ask earlier whether Arduino is
watering down the field of embedded
design I say not um no it's no it's not
it expands the embedded design it gets
more people people into it um you know
you're not forced to you know the whole
industry is not going towards the
Arduino really it's you know it's just
another tool available for people who um
who you know prefer um just to get
something up and running real simple
Heck if I had to get something up and
running um if I had to get you know if
somebody said quick I need something in
you know 20 minutes to um you know uh
set some logic outputs or do something
like that or display something on a new
LCD
um I'm going to reach for my Arduino cuz
it's just simple I'm not going to put a
pick on a breadboard and wiing the
things I might get a pi dev kit out or
something I have but those uino boards
they're like a little dev kit so you
know you can um just get something up
and running real simple so no I don't
think they're watering down the embedded
um field but um you know it's just
another tool um there's always been
things like like the Arduino they're
just you know it's just a different um
just you know a different flavor
really
uh the Ryo 100 MHz bandwidth when the
dexs are running at 100 is it due to
multiple dacks they're adcs not dexs um
analog to digital converters um there's
the analog to digital converters there's
10 of them and they each run at 100 MHz
so they're staggered as I mentioned in
my blog that's how you can get um the
one gig sample per second Dave when will
you when we will see you on Jerry
Ellsworth Channel your voice is loaded
on the text to speech now so you can't
can even see sound like yourself on the
speech bot there what my voice is loaded
on the text to speech where's that
someone's got to someone email me that
link please um don't do it here because
I can't I'm I'm not capturing this
window by the way I forgot to start my
um capture program when I did this so um
this blog probably may not go to air as
a pre-recorded thing I don't know anyway
um so uh Jerry Ellsworth well she
contacted me must have been six months
ago now and um she wanted to know she
liked my channel and wanted to know if
we could do um you know some sort of you
know something something together and
yeah that'll probably happen but I
haven't heard from her again so I might
have to make contact with Jerry she's
pretty cool um maybe I can um get cut in
on one of her shows or she can cut in on
one my live shows or something like that
so yeah that might happen
um multim question have you been using
the agilant
u242 um it's the 1252 isn't it um I
don't have the 1242 I think it was the
1250 no it's the 1253 that's right now I
haven't been using it all that much cuz
I've got so many damn multimers got
multimers coming out my back side um no
I haven't been using it much
um I want to know why elcd modules are
so godamn expensive they're not that
expensive you can get them for 10 bucks
from um various suppliers LCD modules
aren't that bad you can get um dot
matrix Graphics ones little um 160 by um
sorry 120 by 64 um Matrix you can get
dual line displays for like 10 bucks
it's not it's not a problem at all um
you go to uh you can get them even from
Digi key and mous at those sort of
prices I think
um are there any new developments in
electronics that excite you God can't
keep up um a that's too hard a question
sorry
um uh can you manually modify cheap DMM
to be more safeer better input Jacks not
a chance don't even bother don't wait
your time
um please don't delete the water
spillage well yeah I might edit it
together and um and maybe put it up
there maybe without the text chat
Because unless somebody's capturing this
particular text chat so somebody did
catch the whole thing maybe I can um
edit the text on there as well and
upload it as a Blog um but yeah it was
pretty darn funny how ah so
embarrassing spilling water on the
notebook unbel un believable on my first
live for that was hilarious I tell you
what what are the odds of that happening
um want to hear about experience with
engineering for extreme environments um
yeah I'll probably do a Blog I could
probably do a blog or two on on um some
of the underwater stuff I've worked on
um my previous companies I spent pretty
much um almost 10 years I guess at um
underwater electronics companies he's
specialized in underwater Electronics so
um I'm used to you know designing
electronics that goes two kilometers
down on the ocean floor and stuff like
that um so yeah I've got some
interesting Tales there I guess
um I wish I actually documented um a lot
more and um kept a lot of you know I
took more photos and even some video of
stuff I've worked on over the years and
I just I just haven't and oh man I'm I'm
regretting that now really it's just ah
it's just crazy so um yeah I really wish
I uh I had done that um so yeah I don't
have much you know thing many things to
show uh for all my years working those
so you know a couple of documents and a
few photos here and there but oh man
yeah
um Dave when it comes to getting your
home lab set up would you build or buy
your equipment keep in mind students
don't have much money um some things are
worth building power supply are
definitely worth building power supplies
are easy you can get just what you want
you can never have too many power
supplies um so yeah I would um recommend
building your own power supplies as
starters um function gens there's a few
function generator projects around I've
done a couple in the past couple of
simple ones um but gears getting pretty
cheap these days but still even you know
something that cost 200 bucks I you know
that's expensive for a hobbyist um
that's why I recommend you know
secondhand gear on eBay um you got to be
careful what you're buying of course but
so many Bargains to be had so really um
especially in the US um it's worse here
in Australia it's not as good here in
Australia but uh the US is fantastic for
secondhand gear you can set up you know
if you had a big enough uh area you
could set up a lab worth a million bucks
that was worth a million bucks worth of
gear for like you know a couple of
thousand do it's just crazy you can get
your own pick and place machines and all
sorts of stuff it's just nuts um do I
have any patents um yes I have a patent
for uh one of my underwater things um
it's a co- patent um Doug Ford was also
on that uh patent as well um and a bunch
of other guys um that's the only one I
think that's the only one that actually
made it through I did try to get a
patent on my pod sweat um software
program because my brother-in-law who's
a patent attorney talk me into trying to
get you know he wrote the whole thing
for me so um uh yeah I but I didn't go
ahead with that so I got the provisional
patent for that pod sweat program and um
I just you know didn't go ahead with it
because it just I lost interest in it
and yeah so there it sits
um random question what logic family uh
should be used when prototyping
designing digital circuits um hey HC 74
HC is the probably the best the easiest
to get the easiest to work with um so
yeah 74 HC
series
um proper blog about making some lab
equipment um yeah well I'm working on
some stuff so maybe you'll see something
soon well not soon but um you know in a
few months time
maybe
um what is POD
sweat what is POD sweat uh go to
pods.com and you'll find out that's mine
it's my website my software um it's a
gym it's a fitness exercise uh program
basically for your iPod um I did it many
quite a few years ago now I'm not sure
how many years ago and it's a voice
synthesized um my wife actually did the
voices because um what my software did I
wrote this PC software that uh um joins
uh human voices together to like voice
words Snippets to generate a complete um
sentence it's like a Poor Man's computer
generated voice but with a real voice I
know that's not new technology but that
was part of it and then it embeds um the
then it generates a MP3 file for that
and um and then downloads that to your
iPod automatically The Voice
instructions and then the
tags um I use the MP3 tags to actually
embed the text Fitness instructions in
there so you know do 10 reps and things
like that and you know um so it's a
fitness program for iPods and it was I
thought it was pretty darn novel at the
time and um so did my Payton in-law uh
pton attorney brother-in-law who wanted
me to get a pent for it and hopefully
get bought out by Apple or somebody like
that but it never happened I lost one of
those projects I so there's a demo
version available for download but I
never got further than that it's a bit
of a
shame um cuz my attention span isn't
that high sometimes I U just get bored
with a project and go on to the next
before finishing it it's real sad
really um
do I know any analog technology
calculations well um it's a bizarre
question uh you might have to rephrase
that one better um I'm reasonable at
Analog I know how to do I'm you know I
do U analog interfacing lowlevel analog
stuff and I'm reasonably good at it I
like to think
um what do I think of the fluke 17b from
China for 80 bucks it looks reasonable
value um I haven't actually uh laid my
hands on one yet um I might have to
speak to the guy at fluke Australia but
it's only for the Chinese market you're
not supposed to be able to buy it in the
US um so yeah for but for the features
and the fact that it's a fluke and I've
seen inside it someone posted some
photos inside it looks like um decent
internal build quality so you know I
don't know until I get my hands on it um
by the way I shot uh the
first uh multimeter blog yesterday the
multimeter shootout blogger I shot most
of it I haven't finished yet um these
were the
$550 meters and I shot those and I shot
tons of footage for those and I bought
the memory card back in and uploaded the
um images uploaded the video last night
it was like 150 Clips oh God what am I
doing crazy but that were short sharp
you know I'd film each one so the same
test on each meter five times so there's
five videos and then five more and five
more and five more and it's up to 150
Clips already it's nuts man that's going
to take a hell of a long time to edit
let me tell you because the longer the
more Clips I have to edit I've got to
edit each one the start and end and it's
just it's going to take hours to edit
that it's nuts um and that's only the
$50 shootout let alone the $100
shootout um would I buy Scopes off deal
extreme um I haven't personally but a
lot of people on The Forum have and they
give them the thumbs up so deal extreme
um well there's two there's deal extreme
which is the big well-known one and then
there's uh deal Excel or something who
are advertising on the um Forum as well
and um some people have bought off them
and they seem okay um but now you can
actually um tequipment.net you can buy
the ryolf for um
$3.99 I think including um including
postage in the US because ryol dropped
their prices so um there may not be much
advantage to buying direct from China
anymore because you buy from China you
don't get the warranty on the scope so
um it's probably worthwhile now buying
from a reputable dealer like tea
equipment
um what's the time 10 N I uh don't have
too much longer I can probably go for
another 10 or 15 maybe um what video
editing software do I use uh you lead um
well which is bought out by Corell so
it's Corell video Studio X3 I used to
use
X2 um but I just upgraded to X3 so the
last five blogs or something have been
done on the new X3 software and it's
really cheap I got it for like 6 $50 um
so it's really it's really quite cheap
um and it does exactly what I want um
but I've been using that for years so
I'm used to using it um I think it's
really easy to use so um you lead video
studio um and it works really well and
it's got some new um Auto music
Generation stuff in it so the new um
intro and exit um music come from that
they're sort of like an autogenerated
music
um
so when are you going to teach us
Spectrum analysis and compare products
well I need some Spectrum analyzers of
um I don't have a spectrum analyzer in
my lab so um I would have to get one
really to um do a practical
demonstration
um ew Corell somebody hates Carell
there's a Carell hater in the audience
yeah um we know you don't think much of
USB Scopes but what about usb logic
analyzers um yes I've done a log on
logic analyzers um so look that up and
yes USB logic izers are fine in fact I
prefer them over Standalone ones because
Standalone ones take up too much bench
space and really I think they're and
really for a logic analyze you really
need that big screen which you can get
on the PC um there's no substitute for
that so um yeah really unless you got
some huge monster you know uh big
agilant thing with a 1024x 768 screen on
the logic analyzer you're better off
going for one of those cheap USB ones
they're great so yeah um so I don't
think I hate USB based test equipment I
don't the logic analyzers are fantastic
go for it for a couple hundred bucks you
can get a brilliant one um yes but yes
USB Scopes suck because they're much
better um well they can suck you can buy
you can pay good money you can pay
$1,000 for a USB scope and they're going
to be pretty good um but I prefer a
bench
scope
um what is the best to get started with
fpga development board HDL Etc that's a
tough question because there's a
conflict of interest with work so
um yeah let's not go there
um because I actually design fpga
development boards anyway let's yeah
um uh did you ever build spy equipment
yes I did um I've got
let's have a look do I still have
it oh come on where is it where's all
the where's all your books when you need
them hang
on
um no they must be in the archive sorry
um uh yes I built um FM bugs I was
really into FM bugs talking Electronics
um they're still in business I think um
they used to be a magazine um here in
Australia and they did a whole series of
um spy bugs and things like that and
they were great when I was a kid
brilliant they had the PCB attached to
the front of the magazine so you buy the
magazine you've already got the PCB and
oh absolutely brilliant talking
electronics and they got a whole series
of FM bug books you can still buy them
um and I highly recommend them they're
really good yes talking electronics that
brings back some memories Colin Mitch
um who still runs it he still runs the
website I think and good on him God
don't know how old he is now but jeez I
think he wasn't young 20 30 years ago
when I was playing with that sort of
stuff
um are there any interest in Hobby
around the house projects you have done
um yeah there's a few um if you go to
Bab
bar.com um which is a website for my
house you can see some photos of all my
home renovation
projects um so yeah the links out there
um easy to find and yeah that's you can
almost have a guided tour of my house
and projects I've worked on I built a
big back deck um if you go to alternate
zone.com Gallery um I think there's some
photos of my back deck which I built I'm
quite proud of that um I built my solar
sponge air heater solar spun.com uh
which is up on my roof above me um so go
to solar spun.com
uh Dave what do you think about
developing some Community projects from
John MX um yeah Compu Community projects
are great um I don't know if I have time
personally to actually uh work on them
or not um because yeah I haven't don't
have enough time to do the blog really
let alone work on community projects and
my own projects so um you know all the
hacker space stuff there's a hacker
space here in Sydney I haven't visited
yet I've donated some gear to them but
um yeah that's as far as I've gotten
really
um H anyway uh what else have we got
um have you looked into laser
microphones they are pretty awesome
however a lot of do-it-yourself designs
are crap um no I haven't I've got a um
I've got down here
I've got down here a um laser um a laser
distance uh meter it's a laser distance
um controller there's the laser module
and um yeah there it is there and uh
it's I haven't played with this laser on
off it's you know I've got two of these
i' got a couple of these modules it's a
Kean lb70 or something and it's a laser
dist I think it's only for short
distances like a you know a couple of
meters or something like that and it's a
laser distance meter I've been thinking
about playing with that it's not really
laser microphone but I thought I'd just
show you that i' I've had that for years
and really
it's yeah I think I've had that for
about eight years and
uh yeah a key on the front to turn it
off and on it's really Magical Mystery
cupboard
yeah um
Dave has anyone been really
fun don't understand some of those
questions hey Dave what line of
microprocessors do you prefer to design
with um well I haven't done anything
with big dedicated microprocessors for
quite a few years um if I did I'd
probably go um you know arm or black fin
or yeah one of those I don't know I'd
weigh up the pros and cons I'm into
microcontrollers these days most of my
projects fit into because you can get
massive microcontrollers there's you
know not often that I have to use a
microprocessor with external memory and
stuff like that um my designs just
aren't that big they all seem to fit in
the um little you know 86 or 32bit
microcontrollers cuz when you got 256k
of memory 512k in some of these 32 2 bit
micros 32k of s Ram you know you can do
a hell of a lot in um in the 32-bit
micros these days so microcontrollers
are a bit more
Niche
um do your designs consider Eco Green
issues does industry consider it a high
priority
um I'd like to because I'm an
environmentalist but I know in the
scheme of things it doesn't make a huge
difference all this um
RS um stuff is a pain in the ass I think
um because if you go through the you
know it's I mean it's good but yeah it's
a pain in the ass it really um hinders
your manufacturing quality and stuff
like that sometimes it's hard to get
right the industry is really learning
still learning how to get out R HS right
um and um Eco Green issues well you know
no no not really um I'd like to cuz I
know it's not a huge thing if you're
going to design Electronics all the
components are going to come from China
or anything anyway um with with my
projects sometimes I try to use maybe
you know if there's an Australian made
box I'll try and use a locally made
project uh box instead of you know
something from China or or somewhere so
you know I did a little tiny things like
that
um yep
any other questions quick it's 20 n i
better sign off in a couple of minutes
so any last minute
questions no I think the I has the chat
died the chat seems to have died um I'm
not getting oh hang on no sorry yes it
is no I need to scroll
down uh what does it mean when the
oscilloscope is gausian um it's a giian
response so look up um Google giian
frequency response and it's basically
the rolloff well the rolloff of the the
rolloff response of the uh front end of
the scope so yeah go Google
Gan uh filter giian filter response I
think you should get some hits on that
um don't you hate it when Electronics
comes in that terrible impossible to
open plastic yes I hate that um even
just yesterday at work one of our
products at work came in one of those
sealable you know those heat sealed
plastic H things a couple of the M um
one or two of the multimeters for the
shootout came in those plastic things I
think oh really
annoying um yeah I hate
them what other field of Engineers do
you find to have the hardest people to
work with oh god um I don't know I've
worked with software Engineers
mechanical engineers acoustic Engineers
um Ceramics Engineers um materials
Engineers production
Engineers you know all sorts of um
pretty much everyone oh God God I'd have
to think about that production can be
tough but only because I came from a my
previous job was had lots of production
issues and production was a pain in the
earth so off the top of my head I'd say
production engineers
[Music]
um K be sure the ryall soft mod doesn't
mess up the Scopes measurements somehow
no unless I do full performance metrics
on the entire design no but yeah know
just my experience tells me that that's
how they program it at a factory and
they've even admitted as such rol's
actually essentially admitted that um
you know it's you know it it shouldn't
um that the mod is just changing the
serial number in the model number and
bingo it gives you the functionality so
everyone who thinks um that somehow it
ruin it you know it does affect the
performance of your scope and that they
do special testing on the 100 MHz model
I can pretty much guarantee you they
don't I think um when's the next live
blog um well yeah I goofed this one up
totally so um I might do it earlier than
next Monday I'm not sure anyway I'll see
how it goes I'll I'll download the
recorded version see if it's any good
I'll experiment with this webcam again
because it seems to be given a higher
update uh rate than the um the one in
the uh notebook in the E EC notebook
um when is what is my main source of uh
components and hobby projects um H you
know I've got so much stuff at work and
stuff JC Car Fels Fels offer free
postage now um here here in Australia
which is really good RS you know um but
yeah JC Car Al Tronics here in Australia
um has the wife calmed down I don't know
the door's locked she's on that side I'm
on this side so I'll have to go out
there soon um what do your employers
think of the eev blog um they know I do
it and they like it they encourage it
um they encourage everyone to do blogs
and you know blog about the company and
stuff like that but um I'm not allowed
to say anything negative about the
company or negative about their products
in any way or promote the competition or
something like that so that's why
there's a few subjects which I just
deliberately don't touch on the uh blog
because of potential conflict of
interest with work so um even though I
may not get in trouble for it I just
don't want to you know do it and I hope
they don't latch on to it and make me
try and make me uh plug their products
on the blog because I don't want to do
that I want to keep it deliberately
separate so that's why you won't hear me
mention my work at all
um thank you thumbs up day the webcam
has been great audio feel I have an
RF cool no worries guys oh yeah I'll
call it quits um so yeah thanks for
turning up sorry that I absolutely
screwed up the uh The Notebook that was
absolutely hilarious I can't believe it
I was in so much of a rush oh God desk
is so untiy and it just spilled
everywhere
and so yep thanks for joining me guys
and I'll probably do another live vog
soon because it's um fun I think but um
I'll see how the video and audio turns
out so um thanks for turning up everyone
there were like 66 people or something
turned up I'm not sure how many viewers
67 guests and 67 viewers I'm not sure if
that's a coincidence or not but um yeah
thanks everyone for tuning up thanks for
your questions and I got to head to work
and I'll see you next time
bye hi guys I'm on
live am I
up somebody acknowledge that they can
see me on air woohoo thanks
guys you can see me all right just let
me get this chat thing sorted
out and let's see who's online we got
55 viewers one broadcaster that's me uh
and who do I recognize Alan W I
recognize AV freaks Brian Hoskins good
day Brian chemical Oliver I
recognize uh
um DM Landrum I recognize good on you
thanks for turning up guys and uh who
else John MX I
recognize uh who else have we
got Safar I recognize good day
Safar uh who else we got um not sure
anyway good day thanks everyone for
turning up now I've just got follow this
damn chat I've got so many messages here
I love you Dave I love you too Marcel
thanks
uh now I did a trial of this yesterday a
couple of people actually showed up and
um it was really manageable and it kind
of worked so um but now I've got like uh
odd uh people I think 100 people RSVP
but I think think there's some goof up
with the time um somebody sent me a
quick message like a couple of minutes
ago that um the time was incorrect or
something 2:00 p.m. uh pacific daylight
time was wrong I don't know can anyone
confirm anyway it's 8: a.m. here in
Sydney and well I'm here so hopefully no
one's missing out anyway I am recording
just let me double check
that
and I am recording yes I'm recording and
broadcasting so in as high quality video
as I can do um we tried to sort this out
yesterday um and this is basically the
best frame rate we can actually get so
um sorry about that that's just the way
it works but the audio should be uh spot
on because I'm
using if I
can so much [__] here on the bench it's
not funny I'm using my um uh Samsung um
c1u USB broadcasting mic so check one
two um and that works really good now
I'll um show you what the difference is
between the I just sit this over in the
corner here should probably move it a
bit
closer sorry it's
a [__] spillage water spillage hang on
woohoo we have an eer Mercy spilled
water on the laptop this is not
good um hang on we have an emergency I
got to get the sponge
woohoo [__]
sponge
time uhoh knocked over my glass of water
the wife's not happy it's the wife's
notebook I'm in serious trouble here you
go use paper towel hang
on there you go our first eev Blog live
event and I've screwed the pooch
awesome ah love it
anyway um this is pretty bad so just let
me clean this up
and explosion in
by ah how's the chat going there he's
sleeping on the couch tonight no kidding
guys hang on uh yeah just let me uh
remove the notebook and there you go you
get a lovely view of the oh no hang on
this is hilarious it's going live it's
been recorded
fantastic that serves me right for
getting a glass of water ready so my
voice doesn't turn all
horrible which it probably
is this is great I love Live Events they
just work so well
oops the laptop's beeping at me I'm not
sure what's actually
happening something's going be beep be
beep like I'm plugging in and unplugging
a USB peripheral or something um yeah my
voice is fine yes because the mic is uh
really really good and I've got the
sample rate um set to 44k sample per
second and I'll show you that in a
minute once I just get this tidied up
here I'm almost done and
um the camera Dave huh camera
attachments attachments are dying video
is
choppy video is here lag um I don't know
sorry guys I'll catch up on this chat in
a
second and
all right we are good to go again I
think Bloody USB cables it pays to get
uh Wireless that's what tripped over the
um uh tripped over the glass of water
here and woohoo one empty one
full okay we're back on live and and
sorry about that awesome work that was
brilliant okay now is everything working
no video here people are saying they
can't see the video um that's strange
I'm
broadcasting and yeah the notebook's
beeping at me as if um something's been
attached and unattached
that's weird video is back yay you know
the frame rate is going again vid is
okay now definitely one
full getting about one frame per second
um yeah sorry the frame rate is pretty
[__] I don't know what's going on um in
Trials yesterday we really couldn't uh
sort out the frame R frame rate issue it
just is what it is really um so I don't
know if uh if if it's being recorded
okay or not I guess I'll find out when
it's finished and I stop recording so
anyway um yeah what I wanted to show you
is that
um hang
on no I can't actually switch I'm using
Google Chrome here um for the first time
and I can't actually switch over to um
the Google Chrome window so I'm not sure
what's going on there so I'm going to
I'm stuck in the chat room um basically
so I can't I wanted to show you what
happens when I lower the audio um sample
rate from the mic and um yeah I can see
the video frame rate's terrible here too
anyway let's continue um because at
least we can get the audio out of it so
the people who want to watch the
recorded show can get the audio anyway
okay let's go let's start um anyone got
any questions because no don't fire away
yet hang on um because I the reason I
didn't want to present something in this
live uh episode is because um well I
just don't see the point because if I'm
going to um actually prepare something
and do it I might as well do it as a
regular um Standalone blog cuz it's just
going to turn out better so um yeah I
just uh can't see any reason to do that
I may as well interact with an audience
otherwise what's the point of doing a
live streaming event it's like those web
wears right I absolutely hate webinars I
think they're the stupidest concept ever
because they're generally just prepared
material that's just spewed out there to
a live audience because these marketing
[__] think that they're you know oh
webinars the latest Trend and all
Engineers want to watch webinars and
things like that yeah only if we can
interact properly and then they don't
make it available live afterwards it's
just H it's nuts anyway webinars I hate
them so um yeah if I'm going to prepare
decent content and put it out there
don't do it live it's stupid I'll just
do a Blog and upload it um so yeah this
is going to be um totally interactive I
hope so it's a test if it works I'll
probably do it every Monday if it
doesn't well you probably won't see it
again now is the um brightness is it too
bright on the video guys can anyone give
me some
feedback show us your
wife techno junk
I don't think my wife wants to be on
camera there's a few photos of her
around on the web if you want to see her
but because what I've got is I've got
new um I've got some studio lights and
um let me I'll I've got them switched on
so the studio lights now this could be
tragic if I
uh if I goof this up the whole lab's
going to come crashing down but check it
out these are my new um this is my new
soft box I've got two of these things
and they're quite large and they're on
these stands which are like um uh
adjustable up to 2 and 1/2 M High um so
they're really you know decent quality
um
studio uh lighting and I've got those
turned on to help um to help fix the uh
frame rate because the frame rate um of
webcams is going to very
um with um it's going to vary with the
amount of light so if you've got a
webcam and you're getting a crap frame
rate out of it even locally um then you
probably don't have enough light so
that's how it is anyway um let's get
back to the chat professional lighting
yes leads no they're actually um no they
aren't leads they're four um compact
fluos um each 50 Watts I think so
there's 200 WTS total of compact of
daylight um wavelength uh compact fluo
behind that there you go the laptop's
beeping again I have no idea why the
laptop is beeping at me that's just
crazy I hope it's not the water um
that's just that's just silly really
anyway who have we got here tell us
about the outer time license PL
[Music]
y